I'll call to where the Ragnet's got to be in my city council for Monday, August 2, 20, 24.
Public input on to get the personal chances.
Three, claims list.
Motion approved.
Second.
Uncle.
Hi.
He's dead.
Joe, it's a five.
Four claims for radio concrete.
Most two approved.
Second.
Perfect.
Hi.
Don't go.
Five.
That's from July 15, 2024.
I'm going to take an opportunity to bring you up to date on some of the projects we've been working
on since we adopted our economic development action plan.
If you remember we are Jim Fram to do that plan for us, we unrolled that, we unrolled.
We rolled out that plan in early April and ever since then we've had the ground running
in addressing some of the issues that were brought up in that plan.
Tonight I want to focus specifically on one particular item from that plan and that's housing.
One of the things that was recommended from the plan is to begin the form a housing committee
and to begin the process of starting to address some of the needs we have in housing in our community.
The first step we put a committee together, we've got a great committee, a joint working with them.
The first task that they've undertaken is to go out for requests for qualifications from firms to conduct an updated housing and demographic study from Miami and Ottawa County.
So we have been working together with that RFQ to get it ready to go and that RFQ actually went out today.
And so we've targeted eight different firms that have conducted these types of studies in Oklahoma using.
We've reached out to several other municipalities in Oklahoma to ask them how they handled their process.
They're all very forthcoming with information.
That's what this binder is, all of the information that they've provided us along the way we've collected
and put in a bond or label by community.
So it's kind of our reference guy when we were putting the RFQ together from Miami and Oklahoma.
And so it's been a great process. The RFQ looks good.
It did go out today. The deadline for responses is August 30th.
We hope that the committee will meet shortly after that.
RFQ does have a scoring system, they will evaluate each RFQ that we receive, score it,
and then once we rank those firms in order, we will begin the process of negotiating
with the highest score and continue to work our way until we reach a compromise on cost
and those types of services.
So one of the things we're asking you tonight is we're not going to vote, but I want you
to vote on this, we just want you to consider this.
We will come back to you at some point and ask to help in the funding of this study.
We anticipate based on scale of community, scope of work, at this process, could cost
anywhere from $30 to $40,000 when it's all said and now we are not asking you to pay $40,000.
Not even close to that.
We are working with other businesses, other partners, the Mades organization itself,
to understand that our smaller communities, the NIC Bowers from Fairland's already
challenged, all of the other Meres to contribute to this process.
So we don't know what the total cost is yet, we're just lining up partners at this point, and
we would ask that you begin the process of considering helping fund this housing study.
Mades is taking it on, it's our responsibility and ultimately we're going to be able to want
you to pay for that, but this information is going to benefit everyone in the community.
The biggest beneficiary from this study will be the city of Miami, and so we respectfully
ask that you consider that and consider making a contribution to that effort.
Once we get the RFQs back, once we begin the negotiation process, we're going to know what those
costs are going to be, and that's going to help us find, too, and we don't want any one entity
taking on the burden of funding the survey.
We want to be able to spread it out across as many different partners as we can to lessen
the impact, but the reality of the survey is this.
That information belongs to the community, any one who needs it, whether it's developers, whether
it's the city of Miami, Maryland, Kualpa, whoever needs that information, if you ask for it,
you get it.
It doesn't do us any good to go through the process, to spend the money, to do the study, and
then have it sit on the shelf collecting dust.
It can't help us address the critical housing needs we have in our community if no one does anything
with.
So we're asking everybody across the board that's willing to help contribute to that process.
This data is going to tell us a lot of things about our community.
It's going to tell us how many houses we need, but how many houses do we need at each different
level, and what those price points need to be.
It's going to help us in identifying neighborhoods that may be targeted for our neighborhood revitalization
programs.
It's going to help us in identifying potential areas that can be developed that we might
look at.
You had a recent workshop where you talked about things like TIF districts.
It's going to help us in identifying some of those areas and how to best go about funding those types of developments.
It's an exciting time for us, this is a new step for us, going in a little bit different direction.
It's at a time when we're taking all more responsibility than we probably have in a long, probably since the day has a two,
he's not early.
I don't know that major is taking on this much responsibility.
And we do it with myself and a part-time person.
And so, any help you can provide us along the way, we appreciate.
We always appreciate the relationship we have with the city of Miami.
It's a long-standing relationship.
And I think it's going to be a good partnership for us both.
I think right now, I think Mayor Parker and city manager Klein would agree.
We're working closely now.
Then we have in the two years since I've been there.
We're working on a lot of projects that hopefully one day, we'll get to hand the megaphone to bless and he can scream him out from the top of the highest building.
That's our goal.
We'll get there eventually.
The housing was identified as a critical need throughout the economic development action plan.
And so, we're jumping in with both feet.
We're going to get the data that we need.
We're going to put it in the hands of the people who need that data.
And hopefully that will inspire them to go to work.
We'll start building some very immediate homes in our community.
We appreciate it.
Thank you.
That's all I have in station.
I've got personal insight to how much work you put into this.
And I'm telling you right now, I'm really proud of you.
And I'm very thankful.
I appreciate that.
We're doing what city.
I give a lot of crap.
In fact, I want to just go ahead and name some of my community.
They name the community if you don't mind.
Just for a second.
Because that's a great people.
Of course, our partners on that community.
City manager Tyler Klein.
Aaron Klocker from Greg Gateway.
Service on that community as well.
Jason Dollar High for the Burea Housing Authority.
Sean Taylor with our best bank.
Solomon Jones with first-door construction.
I'll get it right.
Who am I missing?
Kevin Crow.
Kevin Crow with Carlton Resources.
That's our housing committee.
They've been meeting either by Zoom or in person.
And they've done a lot of work in a very short period of time.
And so that's why we were able to get that RQ out today.
And less than two months since we've been meeting.
So thank you all very much.
I appreciate it.
Thank you.
Not in revised agreement with my area.
Well, the services for the fiscal year 2425 approved claim until 2005 or no.
The MSUA approved.
But it also includes the claim to 1,500.
It would be the first of the four quarterly payments that we made.
Motion approved.
That's called.
He stepped.
Jack.
Ten.
Stable.
Sir plus property program type of assets management office of management and address services application, which is the same one.
Brian tells us about earlier.
Chris.
Thank you.
Motion approved.
Second.
Perfect.
Done.
Hi.
He's done.
I can jump.
11 contract.
The amendment number one for annual six months.
That's been concrete materials C23.
That's six months.
A.O.
Concrete.
Intended upon submission of all of our contract.
Motion approved.
Second.
Perfect.
Thank you.
He's done.
Hi.
12 declared proposed items listed in the packet.
The surplus authorized items to be offered for public sale or sold for highest
scrap metal value or authorized instruction to protect sensitive information and all the
city managers are.
What's that for?
Sorry.
Perfect.
Thank you.
Hi.
He's done.
13.
Resolution.
In the 1 2 2, 28.
24, B.J.
5 recognize the value of the mind of Senior Center and way the right to assets and authorize
the purchase and transfer of assets to the P.O. rad of Indians of Oklahoma.
So council.
For a couple of months now.
Board of the Senior Citizens Center has been talking with the city and everything about.
What they're wanting to do with the facility that they have.
do with the facility that they have.
We've asked them to discuss with the other stakeholders
and try to work out a degree.
And so apparently, an agreement
hadn't struck between pre-attribes,
and he has in your systems, issues with yards
to the program, which is housed in that facility.
But as of a week ago, Friday, the tribe
has sent to us a resolution asking us to,
in essence, give our blessing to the discussion,
and if that's what you, I think that there are some
still some questions that need to be addressed,
a conversation with you, so just make me a good type discussion.
So, you know, while people speak on this issue,
that's sure to say it, but it's certainly
your prerogative that we, in other words, do a good question.
I think there are representatives from box,
and there are representatives.
I would like to just address you guys tonight and thank you for letting us address the
UNBJ mooney and I'm the Director of Doc Services and on behalf of Docs we have served
Delaware Auto and Craig County's for over 33 years providing senior services, not only
meals, but also toward homemaker services, senior transportation services, outreach services,
registered dietitian services, the dietitian counseling that's needed to our members.
This directly affects us by this directly affects us by not being able to have a kitchen
and a cook site here. The previous director Rick Teele helped to lay out the senior
center when it was built and developed and we will not have a cook site. I'm not going to say
we won't have a cook site. It will be very difficult for us to have a cook site here without having
it at the senior center. The senior center is the ideal location for us. We do have congregate nutrition
sites spread through out our counties that we have. Most recently the state department on aging
urged us to take on more counties that were underserved. We did take on a dairy, turkey, and
Sequoia county. As of July 1 we actually doubled in size and that was because the state asked us to do that
because we have the longevity of our program and the service equality of service that we provide
to the seniors. We are advocating not only for dogs but for the seniors of Ottawa and
of Craig County because it does affect the northern part of Craig County to the northern half of
Craig County. Without a kitchen, there will be over 125 people a day that will not be receiving a hot meal.
Some of these are home delivered. Some of these are at our congregate nutrition site which also provide
socialization activities to and as you know the seniors need to get out and interact to but they also they need a meal.
We ask that you consider that. Consider the longevity of our program. We do manage the gross senior center and we have
for over 30 years there and that's fully manage it not just the kitchen area but we fully manage that site.
through a contract with the City of Grove.
We would ideally like to do that here.
And we have talked about that numerous times for prior to myself, but I have been with
talks for 13 years and that's been discussed for 13 years with numerous people within
the community and city and senior center too.
Do you have any questions for me?
I think that our senior, our doc services, the president is also here and is that allowed
for her to speak and also for a grand gateway.
Do you have any questions?
So you said you started around 25 people a day and that's an all-all-crack County.
That is auto-accounting and the top half of Craig County and those are just hot meals.
That's not our frozen meals that we also provide.
How many of you guys are total total?
We have total in all three counties or all.
No, this could site.
Out of this could site, 125.
Currently, it's just hot meals.
That's the total.
That's just hot meals.
That's the total with hot cold.
The total for hot and cold would be around 2.25 and that's a freezer truck that you see
going around.
Is that the two meals a day?
It's one meal per day.
And that affects meals on wheels, older Americans act, and advantage per gram.
I'm the executive director for Grand Gateway and I know I spoke with you guys several times,
but we fund Docs directly and there has been a push for collaboration between Title VI and Title III
and we were kind of hopeful that maybe we could work something out with the tribe and Docs early on
and we're still hopeful that maybe something in that area
could work out.
The main thing, what it really boils down to, is making sure that those meals are served though.
Making sure that there's not a gap in that service, making sure that those seniors don't go
with cap those meals.
Because for a lot of those seniors, it's their only meal.
They're only real meal a day and for a lot of them, even if it's not their only meal a day,
it's certainly their only hot meal a day.
So, and they really do depend on it's their life line.
So, as far as the funding goes, we fund docs.
So, it's not, it doesn't fall back to the city.
I heard a comment that they were primarily paid for by the city in growth,
but it's not set up that way.
They've got three federal grants, and that funnels through us.
So, I wouldn't want you to think that if it ever fell under your jurisdiction,
you would have to put it in the bill for that.
They are for a stand-alone agency.
And I was contacted to kind of figure out what the original set-up on that was.
And that building was a CDBG grant that would have originally been applied for
would have been owned by the city.
And then the ownership would have transferred to the Senior Citizens Center
because the seniors couldn't have been able to apply for a CDBG grant on their own.
Now, there could have been an older American's act grant that those kicked in there
to help as well.
But at some point it was deited over to the Senior Center.
And then here we are.
So, long story short, I am just advocating on behalf of the people that need it.
But the people that need their meals served.
I would like to see, I would really like to see the tribe and dogs be able to come together
and the title six and the title three program to be able to meet in the middle and collaborate.
Because as I've told you all, when I took over, as a tribal member myself,
one of my main priorities was trying to fill our connection with the tribes.
We have a lot to offer each other and there's so much that we can do together.
And I would really like to see that happen.
But at the end of the day, what we need to do is make sure that those seniors are fed.
So, however we get there, that's what we have to do.
I'm the chairman of the board.
Have been for something like that, but I've been on the board for about 10 years.
And this organization is run very, very smoothly by BJ.
I mean, she's just this thing in darlings here also.
But our main concern is we own duck services, owns the kitchen appliances.
We own all that.
And so, if we have to move someplace else, all that goes with us.
Our funding through, I believe it's OAA is the main one.
No one else is allowed to use the kitchen.
And it's been like that since we've been out there.
It's...
And it's a non-starter for us, for anybody else to say, well, we can't make any promises
we won't use the kitchen.
We'll just have to move.
I had checked with several local people in this past week to find another building.
Of course, that's going to take some time to build out or to lease or anything, or we even
explore maybe constructing a building, a standalone building for just for the kitchen
services for these meals and everything, but it's going to take some time.
And as BJ and Erin have both said, that's our concern if we have to get out, how long
are we going to go, that these people are not going to have a hot meal every day.
And it's 125 people to get a hot meal every single day.
Well, through the week, it's not on weekends.
But I walk in that area, I walk by Park's Lesis House and everything.
And those women are there, or three women are there, every morning, before six o'clock cooking
meals to be delivered at noon.
So we're kind of tweeter rock on a hard place.
We would love to be able to work with the tribe and everything, but in their bylaws and in their
articles and corporation, it says that building will go back to the city of Miami.
It states it in both of them.
So for the senior citizens to be able to give it to the Puri at Tribe, it's just kind of thrown
us for a loop, this bit of that way.
We've been scrambling now for the last three weeks, trying to figure out what we're going to do and
everything.
And we need the city's help to figure out what we're going to do.
And we appreciate anything you can do for us, but I said, we have 125 meals every day of
those people that we're not getting a hot meal.
So we appreciate any consideration you can give us.
Puri, do you want to speak on this?
Please.
Yes.
I will say, I believe that I can probably find some grant funding to get a new facility for dogs.
I do believe I can't, but I also believe that process is going to take probably about two
years.
And I'm going to need some.
I'm going to buy in from the city and the county for that, which I know I'll have, I know
I'll have some support there, but that's just going to be, you know, a couple of years down the
road.
So we've got to figure out what we're going to do here in the meantime.
Good evening, Council.
I'm a great harbor chief of Puri at Tribe.
We come tonight.
We know that there is a great deal of heartburn on behalf of dogs.
We know that.
We've shared.
We've said that on the B.J.
times, I'd say three times, maybe one. And in that, we talked about what our goals were.
Our goals are to help and support the seniors that are in that center now. And so at
the same time, we laugh and say we've got a bit of an unwritten rule that we'll never
building and build another building again that won't have a kitchen in it because so much
of what we do revolves around real. And so we find ourselves with the opportunities to support
the senior center at a level that we're excited to do. But there is an issue with the lack
of there not be in access to a kitchen. And so we shared with a journey, been more than we
all sat down together one after and talked about what the issues would be, could be. And we
know that this is a real issue. And so when that, when Docs talks about their access to the
kitchen technically, it's just a 30-day month to month right now by the contract that
obviously. And so I shared with Ms. Mooney, I said that, you know, one or two things happens.
Purely says, welcome and stay forever than we know it to do. I said it, Purely, you know,
lost our mind and said, be out tomorrow. We also know that it could be out for six months, not success.
And I said, let's agree to do nothing until in the year because her team has a
networking, our team has a networking, all those collaborations that Purely can be frank.
We're good at it. It'll take some time down, we're able to have those meetings, the have those opportunities
to do that. And so we're excited to wait and see how this goes. We have, we have no interest in seeing
on 125 elders lose their meals. Not as completely off-brand to what we do. They talk about title six
and title three, title six on our side of it. Us and the audit was partnered together. Those were federal
dollars, it's out by the complex where all of our offices are at. And in order to make sure,
we have such high level nutrition, we partnered with the auditals. Two weeks ago, this last year,
we raised, you guys know, we got a cattle farm out east of town. And we took five of those animals,
raised them up, put them through nutrition program. I had a pop-all scuttle. We sent them down.
That has nothing to do with title six. We're not paid for that. We donated that to that program.
We are all in brand to feed our elders. We're downtown right behind the new feeds,
building a food distribution center now. And so we value nutrition. It's obvious. And so anyway,
as we know it's going to take some time to walk this out with dogs. But frankly, right now, we've got
a agreement between two governing councils. As a governing board yourself, you know that that doesn't
always happen. We've found some really great partners here at the Senior Center. They go to
unanimously to see this partnership come to fruition. Our business committee is tomorrow night. We have a
resolution before us.
you guys have wanted to accept it and so are elected officials or beyond excited to see this kind of through.
So we know it'll take some time.
I don't know we have, we see the elders there at Senior Center with meals that come through what we do.
It'll just take a little bit of time.
So we presented this opportunity.
We were presented with an opportunity.
We presented the same opportunity to sit in.
So we were at Goes.
And so again we're very excited to work with my Senior Center.
It's been a great work to cooperate with that answer.
So the more understanding that if the tribe comes in, the dogs will have to leave.
They can't share the space.
Well we've asked what we've asked and I've shared with them.
I still see a Saturday with a football game on and for the first time in 10 years I'm excited about college football.
I don't even know why.
But we're talking about it.
I've got chilly on my mind and I said we're going to go chilly and we're going to have those times together.
But I know we can't do it in a microwave.
And right now that's what Senior Center has access to because of the word the kitchen is.
We're not asking them to change the rules.
We just know that there's a very big commercial kitchen on the other side of the door that the Senior Center doesn't have access to.
And so that's where that's where the crux is.
It's not that we don't want to agree.
Yeah, agree.
Sorry, we told you.
We told you.
Right. Right. Right.
And we have to keep our kitchen completely separate.
Yeah.
It's a draw.
That draw. That's what draws the line.
Not not not this team or our team.
It's a.
And I should not at all even know you're not available again.
Because it's yours.
We know that they'll be a time where we hope to see access to it to cook there at that facility.
Because that's what we do.
We also know that that puts a burden on docs of changes.
They're entire model up.
We know the equipment is theirs.
We've already committed the dollars to win it comes time to purchase new equipment for that facility.
We know what those are.
You guys will see in our learning center.
And what's the old campus?
You guys will see in our community center or the old country club.
We remodel the club house, the community center and the learning center all three of those.
I fully stock.
Billy operational commercial.
We know exactly what we're looking at.
There'll be a time we believe when it comes to that.
But the goal is not to have nutrition evaporate on behalf of elders.
And so we know there's going to take some time.
But we also know that's.
We can't make decisions.
We can negotiate with docs because we don't have access to it.
We're not.
We're not in control of the facility.
Right.
So.
So let's talk about.
Somebody brought up that the building had to come back to the city, Ben.
Let's talk through that.
What does that look like?
The art also the incorporation of the Senior Citizen Center, as well as the bylaws in your
Citizen Center, say that if they dissolve as a corporation and all the assets that they have
to go to the city, there is another provision that whatever reason if that doesn't work
then the district order would decide.
The raises a question that I'm a little bit confused.
Just last week we got the minutes of the Senior Citizen Center where they boven to approve
this arrangement.
Sixth, it says that Emotion was made by Bill,
to sign the Resolution if needed for the transfer of the Senior Citizen Center to the city
of Miami.
I'm wondering if it was a typographical area.
But I would have to take a look.
The pre-seating area I have said that you were going to transfer it to the tribe.
This next paragraph says you're going to transfer it to us.
So I'm thoroughly confused.
And both of them are approved by the board as a six o'clock.
That's kind of what I figured it was.
So let's go back to like, when this building was built, what funds were used to build this building?
The CDBG grant which is a community to build a lot of grant.
It would have had to have been sponsored by the city.
So the city would have had to have been the initial owner of the building.
And there's a 10-year window of transfer on that.
So Cindy would have had to have owned it for a 10-year,
and I got to think about this.
Probably why you saw it, I believe the building process,
the construction process started around 1990,
probably completed, fully granted, around 93.
That's probably around 2002, or so.
When ownership was probably transferred to the senior center,
it would be, I guess, now I haven't seen any documents to confirm that.
But I believe that's probably about the time that the city also started,
probably giving utility credits and whatnot to that.
And you would probably see that showing up on your books as well.
That probably coincides with about that time.
And so, if the city did have ownership originally of the building,
transferred it to the senior center.
And we have not found those documents and policies
that have allowed us to get rid of those kind of documents
after seven years of their building.
But our financial program that goes back to 2000 and 2004,
excuse me, a year, that indicates that it goes back
for 2000, to the year of 2000.
But from 1990, when this whole program began to 2000,
we have found no records whatsoever.
So we don't know how much money the city is putting
in and all together, but with records, we have show that we put $700, $18,000
into the program.
And we think we've put in another $1,000 to $2,000.
Those dollars include utility credits as well.
That includes the utility credits that taxpayers $1,000.
Yep, just making sure that you added that in there as well.
So the agreement between the senior center and the purry tribe is just the transfer of a building and that's it
It's just a transfer of building nothing coming back. Not buying it. They're just you're giving it in the building 10 dollars
So what does that look like from the label perspective because at some point this language kicks in that this thing is dissolved
So if they have don't have ownership of the building anymore, then it's not the citizen's responsibility to take over ownership
Chain custody with the back of us and then to them
There that's a complicated legal discussion
I know, but I mean this is a complicated situation. So we need to make sure we cross all of our T's and all all of our eyes
I just think we'll discuss that in the executive session. So be right. How big of a facility do you need to operate in to do these meals?
How big is the current facility?
So we have a contract this was set up many years ago and this is what Doug Mart is talking about
center that the senior center board wanted to be able to resell the meals so they do contract
with this and resell their own meal. Our services, docked services, we do not charge for
our OAA program, we do not charge for our advantage program.
What's the OAA example?
Older reasons, I've heard. We contract with 350.
They received the 350. Well, we received the 350 for preparing the meal the food costs and
they received their dollar for the goods and so these are for seniors that are not signed up.
Through the Older Americans at program, yes. It is a state law within the state, it's considered
double the being the sites. We're through our free of charge and we do not.
How long did you say?
We're lucky to eat all the apples.
Move it right.
We have to build something with you.
And if we really feed our people, which is...
So let's say a perfect world.
I'm just throwing this out there.
It takes two months because you have a place and you can just move right in.
How do you provide meals during that transition?
Would there be a period of time that you couldn't...
...from what Craig County, our Delaware County.
This is a part where we have absolutely hate about all this.
Waiting not like this either.
I hope you all know that.
Thank you.
My name is Gayford Child.
I'm the acting president.
I was the vice president.
That's been our world.
It was president.
She resigned.
So...
We took over in January.
But we had to take over the office.
We're the whole shabining of doing this.
We'll through all of this.
Dean your center is so low.
That we did not see how it could stay open.
If some catastrophic something happened, we would be totally...
...so we were trying to come up on what to do to keep this senior center open.
Everybody and we went to the end and we asked him first of all because we know there's that clause in there about the city
We brought into the city
He suggested possibly that you gift it to the tribe if I would want it, so that's where we went from there
We've got less than 70,000
So we just figured either seniors and needs to go to somebody to ran it properly or it's going to close
We don't have money from programs. All we have money is to keep that center open for
View games, go over few carcans. We don't have any programming. So gay the conversation was that as long as everybody gets protected
How much were we trying to do?
Where at? How did I approach?
Who made?
I don't want this to be a piece that she said and I think that's kind of what it's going into and I know it's taking up your guys this time too
But we also want to get all the information out there. We do fully run and stuff this senior center there
We have a full-time site manager there and then we also have our kitchen stuff there and we have for many many years
You know there's there's a lot and it is difficult when you have a volunteer board and
Information is not always passed on, you know, it is it is a way of life. It is people step up
And we're glad to have the volunteers and that they do they do step up. It was also disgusting
with people within the city at different times, you know, that we would like to
we understand the dilemma.
I think that there were other grants that possibly would have been available for the senior
center to keep their doors open.
But again, it is a volunteer board, and that is...
How long has Docs been in the senior building?
We helped to lay out the building before when it was being built.
So Rick Teele actually helped to lay that building out.
So with 30 years, my question is not trying to be sarcastic
that by any stretch it may sound that way when it comes out.
But I don't mean for a dude.
The senior and Docs have been in the same building for 30 years.
And now we're here.
We are.
And the city and the tribes have been brought into something that you guys just...
You guys have been in the same building for 30 years and you haven't communicated with each other
of them.
We have communicated.
When you get volunteer, we're someone who has been here, say, hey, this is what it's been
all these years.
So if they've lost all that information in that it's not their fault, it's just the way it happens.
When they're volunteers.
So I guess what you guys like to re-incapate?
When you came on, and this is not being sarcastic at all.
But just when you came on, did Bo or anyone because you have a hundred million things under
you know that you're doing under your one hat?
Did anyone say, hey, the senior center?
Docs has talked to us about managing the senior center.
No.
Okay.
And that's a learning curve for students.
It's a lot to take in, and that's with anything, and especially when you have volunteers.
You know, you understand.
It is difficult.
So because there are a lot of the nature of questions, that's why at least my recommendation
details can be worked there.
But it's a significant detail.
they face on a month of weeks. There's been a lot of hard work about boogets, fuggets to use for learning
center, not wearing a mouth out of it, takes in all of your parents were here for a homemade
job for a couple of times, and she went around, she couldn't bring her friend to the singers
and should this get her fruit. Or if I take it, it's a bit crazy. Oh, I understand.
I'm just like a golf horse. I said.
Sixty and above, no?
I think they probably need to be directed to us.
Okay, so it was, um,
so I'm calling for statistics and it's not going to, it's not going to, it's not going to.
new to the senior center. I don't know if you're aware, but through Green Gateway there are
grants specifically for the senior center up to $12,000 a year. I know that's not a huge
amount, but it is $12,000 a year, and they are poor just daily operations. I just didn't
know if you knew about that.
I guess my question is if they can, if they are the owners and they can do what they want,
what is our involvement, what do we need to even be involved as the city?
My name is Darling Miller, and I am employed with Doc Services, but my question is not in that
direction. I'm amazed that a city like my Emma and the growth that we have, the potential
that we have, the marketing we have, that we're going to be able to say, no, we don't have
any place for senior citizens. If we close our senior center, let's
that sound like. Nobody's, I mean, we are not in any attention or provide anything for the seniors
that go. If the senior center closes.
I don't think anybody is saying anything about the senior center closing. I think that's why we're
here, because they want it to remain open.
I don't know.
But I'm just thinking, and end of the umbrella of the city of my Emma, and you do your marketing
and those other things. If not everybody's going to know that, I just think that the city
could be very proud of the senior center that's run and run for all, because there are some
who don't go because they're not aware or whatever with anything that the archerites have.
You know, it goes under there, and I'm not at member. My husband, the member.
And I can tell you that there's a couple of things. There's a beautiful...
facility that you have at the complex where the country club used to be. I can't use that.
It's all strictly for the tribal members. Now my husband, my grandchildren, and all
our boys and all that, yeah, you know, that works and fine. But there's a whole bunch of
people here. Not when we did it. No. No, no, no. It had to be a tribal member. And yes,
we rented it. And it's absolutely, yeah, under my granddaughter's name, it's a tribal member,
but I could not do that. That's a personal experience. I don't want this to turn into a
bowler, but we appreciate you. We do. We do. We understand what my head has there. That's
wonderful, but it's struggling right now. We recognize that there's a struggling situation
and on both sides. Definitely on both sides. Even G-Farckers, like it's a complex situation.
We really need to discuss it for. We need to discuss it for further. We need to
discuss it for further. We need to, exactly, to session. We don't want this to come out where
people don't like each other. We want this to come out the resolution where there's many people who
just give me, you can be happy. Um, a large set of the seat that never is everybody gonna be happy,
but if we can try to make most of you happy, then we win. But, um, you know, I don't
Chief Harperwell, that will weigh into my decision for our friendship because he is a
friend.
But we'll make the decision that we all feel comfortable with and take
executive and let the legal counsel, and I don't know Chief Harperwell understand
that we're a decision we make, and I hope everybody else will take, and I don't think
that the senior citizen center is what's a question.
He's committed in front of all of us and it'll be open to everybody, six or seven days
week.
He said it on the record of Rireby, the question is the kitchen and the
doctor program.
And that's a concern everybody.
So that's where we'll be.
I don't think we're really concerned about the senior center.
He's already committed to that being open.
So, yes, ma'am.
Some of you know this, some of you may not.
But up until last week, my mother was homebound in bed in my living room.
And Knoxville served her meals every day.
So, I understand clearly what you're saying.
My mother passed away last week and and Knox showed up to deliver.
and then I appreciate what they do.
I don't think they're saying by here
that I was going to appreciate what they do.
This is an issue, I'm not sure
it's working build effects to take the truth.
I mean, you know what I'm not sure
they're saying buying this room that doesn't want people
to get their meals.
We just need to figure out how.
There's a compromise here.
That's what we're going to come in.
I think the important thing to remember is
she brought it up when she said
that this couldn't continue.
So if they let things continue as it was,
she said it without saying it.
This whole building shuts down
and then wears docks, because this had to happen
one way or another.
I truly believe there's a compromise here.
And I believe there's a compromise here that's
going to benefit everyone.
And I think if once we go to executive session,
and we all talk, we'll probably come to something
that we can present to you guys that may help sell this.
We hope this may.
So that's what I was going to ask.
When this new regime took over, did you guys go and talk to them
about taking over at that point?
So it sounds like it wouldn't be because we use that kitchen
for a city of man's.
And we, that's the, that's kind of a problem.
That's the kitchen.
The kitchen is even for cheap harbor is
that socks need to do it.
We would build all these art kitchen and if he takes
the building, he would build the kitchen and they're either.
So that's, that's kind of the issue here.
And we know it's, it's not one that you created,
but it is, but it's one we all have to live with.
So we're going to figure out how we can make work.
One more question, you said you guys have $70,000 a roughly, so that is a asset that
also be transferred along with the building, okay, anybody before we move on to the next one?
Okay, so you have the agenda item in front of you, you can approve the risk, or you can take some other action,
but there's also the executive session that you're in the agenda, discuss things, and also a lot.
So, I want the motion that we table 13 to add to that.
I don't think we have a motion for that.
I think we just have to take no action at this time until I predict the intersection.
I'm just wanting to make sure you understand.
What are the motions?
How do we need to know lately?
The motion of the day to the question?
I think we take no action at this point.
You could just take no action at this point.
Then would you want lately when you'd advise us to do this one?
You think about it there?
I would say, take no action.
Until I predict a number of different action.
No action on it.
This is the agenda item.
So, we'll take the action along the agenda of 13.
You go to 14.
Jerry, some of Jerry, Jerry, or some of Jerry Kramer, arrangement, plan, and GR,
Jerry Kramer, agreement, and template.
So, I'm just going to keep this short and sweet, because y'all know I get real long-winded.
So, let's just go ahead and jump.
Let's just take a look at the agreement.
So, let's go back.
I did tell you guys a little bit that I wanted to set up a payment plan for the citizens of Miami
to help in the end of life process.
So, everybody knows that planning a funeral can be burdensome.
And so, when those left behind don't have the money to carry out your wishes,
it can already turn this stressful time into something that's unbearable.
So, we want to help encourage at GR pre-planning.
And so, in order to do that, we want to offer the citizens of Miami a way to
pay.
payments for a plan. We feel that it will really help and broaden what we have to offer
there at GAR. So this contract will allow citizens to select a plot and make 12 equal payments
to complete their ownership. This contract will be for the plot only. No other fees will be included
such as the opening and closing the setting fees or the mark of fees. And the debtor will not be
allowed to intern or intern on set plot until the agreement is paid in full. But by allowing them
and breaking this down into 12 monthly payments, you can break it down as low as $45 a month for one
and that's for a Cremain's plot. So for an internment plot, you can break it down to almost $60 a
month. So being able to provide that option to our citizens is showing our citizens that we
we care about their end-of-life process and we care about, you know, moving forward with them in this
tough time. There are some fees to set up the program so there would be $125 admin fee to start the
contract and if there was any return checks, there is a non-sufficient fund fee of $25. So that's kind of how
we have a set up out of now. So today we're coming to you in conclusion. We're kind of coming to you today
to present the contract which you guys have been able to see been able to read and we are just
asking that you allow us to get started. So we know there may be, you know, some, you know, small speed bumps
along the way but allowing us to get started and helping our citizens we can kind of see for one if we
have, you know, great interest in it and for two, it will allow us something to at least build on
and I think that's the most important. Do you guys have any questions?
I have a question about default. If any reason the debtor should not apply to any section of portion of the
agreement the debtor shall be considered in default under such an event the agreement will become an
only void. No refund will be given to the debtor of any kind and we'll understand that. I can't help but
empathize and put myself into this situation at the time of my life when I would probably
be making decisions like this. Sure. It seems a little...
Have you handed if I guess maybe the word short, so let me explain why we're doing
Okay, um, and I knew the thought is gonna be a big issue
The reason for that is because we are gonna be tying up property
We're getting ready to open up. I had to say prom real estate
But we're gonna ready to open up new areas at GAR you guys fully aware of that
We are extending
The GAR in the peace. We help to eventually get a new colabarium
We still have the Mosulian. We've got places right along the road which is always a
Huge
Area because you know nobody wants to walk all the way back to the fence
You know to bury their loved one
So since we're getting ready to open up these new areas tying up that area and keeping it from blessed or from cabbage
Or from Molly keeping the keeping that tied up for a year
You know where you was a cash payer can't come in by that property
I mean we feel is my concern is that a more like at the end of
My term and
Something happens to me and I pay 11 months of this. I really like my daughter to come in and just clean up
I mean you know absolutely absolutely and so we would definitely
Confident that she would right that is not something just because like if you step past the way 10 months into the program
We would definitely you know allow
You know the next
You know person in line the trustee the executor or whatever to come and make the final payments on the
On the property so they could
We're not that hard
So where we would take that away no the the next person in line or your husband or your wife or your children
But would have the option to make those last two payments
You know in order
You know to create what we would call ownership at that time
It's covered
The way it's written the one
I emphasize this is a pre-being
Right
Allow somebody to not pay the whole amount
Which is when they are in need they have to pay and that's difficult for some people
But the reason we have it this way is once there's so many in the ground and makes it a whole lot harder to
Repossess the part sure
Right
So just so
So this is to try to cover
It's to help people do it
But it still protects the city
And like I said the other you know, this is gonna be a learning process for all of us
This isn't something that we've had
you know, in the past. This is something that is kind of a vision that I came with, you know, when I started, you know, to be able to provide that.
And exactly what Ben said as a pre-need basis, you know, and offering, you know, bite-sized payments to our citizens of Miami.
And instead of offing them, you know, at the hardest time in their life to fork up, X amount of dollars.
And she really discussed, so we fully, just to see what kind of agents we just don't know what the agents are saying.
And is there already doing a great job? I'm telling you, these are great. Just that one scared me to fall.
Quick question.
With my mom this past away, she had a policy for her burial.
Of course, it covered the funeral of the arrangements on that.
And her, as it was an insurance policy. So, you know, she paid on it for four, five years, 50 bucks a month.
And then if she passed away for a paid off, it was like an insurance policy that we were done.
Is there a way to do something like that with this?
It's something we can look into. This was just phase one of trying to reach out to the citizens to say, we're going to try to offer something.
I'll tell you, it made a lot easier on me because she planned everything.
All I had to pick was the day and the time and the casket.
But I don't want to get this confused, pre-planning for a funeral home and pre-planning with our cemetery.
So, our cemetery is only offering up the plot of land.
So, at the funeral home, we'll still be the ones that does all the other like the services and that's where the majority of it will come from.
That's why they can extend that to you for a five year program because that particular amount is about, I mean, let's just be honest, it's almost buying a car.
And so, they can spread that out over a five year period.
To where we are offering a 12 month break it down, our services are obviously a lot less.
So, you're not going to need five years for that.
I can pay that off.
The other difference is that an insurance company is an insurance company.
They do actually where real studies to determine how much they are selling.